then the venerable upana went to the
Buddha and said to him bante it is said
that the dharm is evident and what way
is the dharm evident not involving time
verifiable and ushering to be
experienced by the wise for themselves
Opana take a biku who sees a sight with
the eye he feels both the sight and
passion for the sight there being
passion for sights internally he
understands there's passion for sights
internally for me this is how the Dum is
evident not involving time verifiable
and ushering to be experienced by the
wise for themselves so on with hearing
smelling tasting touching and
cognizing now take a biku who sees sight
with the eye he feels the sight but no
passion for the sight there being no
passion for the
sight for the SES internally he
understands there is no passion for SES
internally for me that is how the dhama
is evident not involving time verifiable
and ushering to be experienced by the
wise for themselves so
on so which number was it this was
Samaya 3570
so usually it's thought of that
um you abandon the
fits kind of like
later you have something in your mind
something that you're revolving around
and then you sort of do something so
that at some undefined period of time
later that thing goes away
and that's how purification is conceived
so inherently that involves
time but here the Buddha is saying the
dhama doesn't involve time and he's
talking about something that might
easily be overlooked because it says
passion for sights
internally um it doesn't just say
passion for
sights so what could
so what could
we come up with as a practical
description of what that's what they just
said well what comes to mind for me
first is it's kind of taking away your
excuses in the sense of you might say oh
you know well sure right now I am like I
like oh it's just I'm passionate you
know I haven't I haven't gotten there
yet but this is kind of saying no there
is something that is within your control
that you're doing right here right now
that can be stopped so it kind of takes
away the room for that excuse
um but again it's kind of comes down to
figuring out what is within your control
and it's
not so what is that passion internally
like uh you already kind of hinted at it
but is it um something that comes by
itself well no it's something you're doing it's
well no it's something you're doing it's
an action so does it mean that if you
just stop doing something it will
disappear immediately well
the well you have to kind of be able to
distinguish between passion and feeling is what that
between passion and feeling is what that
s was talking about yes so in a sense it
doesn't it's not that it um it's not
that fully it's just you doing it
because then you might think okay so I
just have to find the perfect trick for
it to cease immediately and then you're
going to basically just frustrate
yourself trying to find out what the
missing um sort of Eureka moment is but
um in a sense it does come by itself
like feeling as the Buddha said the tendency
feeling as the Buddha said the tendency
for the underlying Tendencies are
beginningless so you don't need to start trying to be
so you don't need to start trying to be
lustful start trying to be averse start
trying to be ignorant it's enough from
the starting point that we all begin in
to have a pleasant feeling that's enough
for lust to be there having unpleasant
feeling enough a verion to be there
having a a neutral feeling enough for
distraction carelessness to be there so
it does come by itself in the sense that
you didn't um it's not a choice that you
consciously made um but at the same time it is you
made um but at the same time it is you
you are responsible for it because it's
something that like there is a choice you're
that like there is a choice you're
making that is maintaining it that's
yeah yeah there's a choice you're making
that's maintaining it and that if you
stop making it you would actually fix
the problem even though the symptoms are
still there and that's where the that's
where the um tough the tricky part comes
in because the natural expectation is I
want the whole thing to
disappear and you feel usually a sense
of guilt like because you did something
and these thoughts are now coming up and
you implicitly feel that sense of like
okay I created this now I have to get
rid of it as soon as possible
and the the point there is that the
passion internally like you you
basically disregard
any uh explanation involving time of why
this passion came to be it doesn't
matter if genuinely you did something un
wholesome something happened something
unexpected right
now if you allow yourself to act out of
craving in regard to that passion either
to continue indulging in it or trying to
get rid of it that is your passion now
like the other stuff that that's there
on its own the pressure the the the
feelings the thoughts that's not now
that's not in your
control back then sure you could have
prevented it if you hadn't been careless
but you can't undo what you did in the
past so now this is the state of your
Aggregates and um what you're doing now
internally is as simple as just um
giving into it or trying to get rid of
it it's that tiny little um choice
choice to to yeah like to lean in either
of those two directions so um and that's
the part that that cuz yes there is Cal
the just talked about you know the Mind
calming down and and um samadi and all
that stuff but that is none of that is
permanent like um the thing is you are
going to to have these pressuring States
sooner or later and you know when stuff
happens in life and if you think that
only when these things don't arise your
practice is going
well well inevitably your practice is
going to fail at some point from that
perspective uh so you need to basically
recognize that uh absence of
that uh absence of
craving and a Calm Mind are two
different things and
wholesomeness the wholesomeness that you
need to worry about is the absence of
craving Calm Mind comes as a result of
the absence of craving so if right now
you have a uh whatever it might be
whatever hindrance whatever pressure it
might be now you make a choice not to
act out of craving in regard to it but
truly like you again not involving time
you're not like expecting because that's
a problem um usually the the you say
okay I'm going to endure this I'm not
going to act out of it but why because
you still like if you ask yourself what's
still like if you ask yourself what's
going to happen how would I feel if
tomorrow it's still there it's clear
that you would be bothered so you need
to undo that
expectation and just endure it basically
for its own sake and then that's where
on that internal level you don't have
craving and then as a I mean the the
problem is fixed like I said the ill the
illness the actual illness is fixed but
the symptoms are still there and if you
uh keep the illness out of the picture
for a sufficient amount of time then the
symptoms will go away as well but that's
that shouldn't really be your concern
like as soon as as long as you're still
concerned of how when when will the
symptoms go away you won't be able to
undo the illness properly
that's one of the things I was thinking
when you mentioned this topic to bring
up like how does it actually relate to I
suppose the correct understanding
of it's talked about like the centrality
of patience and endurance and all of
those things have this immediate
implication of involving time I think
patience I must be patient patiently
endure this your pressure and and not be
kind of in a rush to like immediately
see it or fix it right away and so there
is a kind of correctness in that but
then it also kind of gets this
implication of so I must patiently wait
for the craving to kind of go away on
its own somewhere over there so like
how's the what would be the correct how
do they actually go together then yeah
be patient so that dot dot dot
but yeah so how can you be
patient without without involving Time
Yeah by allowing to manifest whatever
has to manifest and basically not act
act out of it that will be your level of
patient or
impatient and obviously like the thing
is you're going to have that information
in your mind you're going to know yes I
shouldn't act out of it but you even
that will not be enough like you will
need to keep yourself in check because
at some point like I said the the
underlying Tendencies are are like just
waiting to to to jump in and uh
especially most especially if you
haven't been developing the
prerequisites of of virtue sensor
strange seclusion like the wrong
attitude is going to come back and
you're going to notice like two months
later if if if ever so um that's why those
if if if ever so um that's why those
prerequisites are not optional because
those are the things that allow you to
at least contain how far you can um how
how far you will go in either of these
two wrong directions of overly giving in
or trying to get rid of stuff because
that's what happens when you break your
restraint and stuff the natural uh
result is is the sense of guilt like I
just said and then because of that like
you can't help it that whole push is
there for you to resolve the situation
as quickly as possible and that
undermines your ability to to be truly
patient on that right level so that's
why uh that's like the result of action
in a more um the most acute way not like
you know what's going to happen in your
next life In This Very life you end up
having to deal with these mental states
that you yourself are not able to
properly um endure and and uh
understand on account of you doing stuff
that you knew was UN wholesome from the
start and that's um that's why it's a
it's a gradual training
like that's why the Buddha would start
by telling the person okay develop your
virtue once the virtue is developed he
would move on to the next one and then
once that's develop you move on to the
next one so if you've been let's say
breaking precepts and then you catch
precepts and then you catch
yourself what would be the how you
practice that Timeless patience you want
call it
that well acutely you don't want to try
to get get rid of the guilt like you
don't want to now be kind of
perpetuating the same thing that you've
been doing when you were breaking the
precepts just now applied to the guilt
of breaking the
precepts so I
mean often you can kind of say you're
being indulgent and then you can kind of
Swing the other way like oh I need to
like kind of Double Down punish myself
for this it is just like you don't want
the guilt to be there but what would be
the best way to just actually fix the
problem and uh not
introduce other variables that are going
to distract
you let's say you're feeling pressure to
keep breaking the precepts and not just
like um you're at you're still at the
stage where you haven't established your
virtue let's say like you still
genuinely feel almost like automatically
you end up doing these things
well you need to reflect on kind of the
benefit of following the precepts while
that pressure is not there but that's
okay I said a while it's still kind of
saying later well let's say like right now
later well let's say like right now
you've you I don't know you broke a
precept two days ago or something and
you still feeling the pressure I you're
basically kind of feeling totally
confused I feel like I am compelled to
keep doing this and it's a a pressure at
the same time I know I shouldn't be so
so I know I shouldn't but at the same
time it's like pressuring me and at the
same time I'm feeling guilty so so let's
let's let's say too too confused let's
say it's not like like um like you
already restrained yourself it is like
you are about to actually give
in like so we're not talking about some
who who would be like withdrawing and
then reflecting like okay I shouldn't
have done that no there like someone who
is about to just just a total beginner
hasn't been keeping any sort of behavior
good behavior in their life and they
genuinely feel like one slip and they're
back into um lying killing
whatever the answer is quite simple
actually is it just don't yeah
exactly all you can do is not do it so
at that
stage like you have to the
defilement that was there is destroyed
the moment you just don't do it so um
the problem is like you might like you
said you might be thinking okay so now I
have to get rid of the guilt and and or
or or do something more than this
basically and that's what would actually
distract you from the fact that no the
pressure that I have right now is to
break the precept and if at the same
time with that pressure I have the
patience in regard to it it cancels out
so you you you balance it out to the
same extent that it's there and then
only later when you don't no longer feel
pressured to break these precepts and
you feel like
okay now it's other stuff that my mind
is revolving around like just thoughts
but not really the the actual actions
out there in the world then you realize
over time okay now there is a more
subtle layer here that I can deal with
and on that on in the same way that you
would simply refrain from killing an
insect you can now refrain from giving
into thoughts of s neity aversion and
distraction so that's why it's like um
the Buddha gave a simil of a gradually
purifying gold and he said it starts
with the uh UNH wholesome actions by
Body speech and mind which is like you
know when the gold is just freshly
taking taken out of the mind or whatever
and then um gradually you get it to the
point where it's just uh gold dust and
then it's ready to be turned into like a
you know a bracelet or something so
you can't be you know doing the the the
melting when there is still gravel and
dirt in the gold so that's why it's a
like the Buddha wouldn't be talking to
people about yeah so you know two years
from now when you have developed your
virtue and and your sense strength
you're going to be doing this and this
it's like precisely right
now you develop that Timeless principle
starting with your virtue um you don't
you you you're not waiting for something
else to happen in order for you to be
able to keep the precepts you realize
right now at at this moment there is an
opportunity to break this precept and at
the same time there is a choice to not
do
it and uh that's already developing the
principle of B this yeah and and and
like the also important point there is
like the refraining from doing is what
that is kind of opening up is the
recognition that there there is that it is a choice
that there there is that it is a choice
to break the precept because any like
breaking any precept or acting out of
any pressure what that has in common in
whatever kind of situation is that it
feels like a compulsion feels like I'm
under a a kind of a compulsion I must I
must do this and then the problem that
can also happen is that you can well you
probably would initially then just be
kind of replacing it with another sort
of okay I must just sort of not do this
I must sort of do something else but if
you just kind of um don't allow this one
to happen to that extent it's it's
already kind of
um yes just canceling out that layer of
um of the defilement that was causing
you to do it so allowing you to kind of
um remove that layer that you get to
kind of see another one that kind of
carries all the way through because
ultimately what you can kind of realize
is like that sort of sense of like you
know I'm under pressure to to I must
tell a lie in this situation I can't you
this person just can't know the truth or
whatever and it what what you can
ultimately realize is like it is that um
it's it's it's your craving and nothing
else that is the the source of that kind
of compulsion and if and if you were to
kind of if you were to be able to stop
craving in that situation to stop kind
of resisting the unpleasantness of the
idea of this person knowing the truth or
whatever you would have literally no
reason there would be no reason to to
need to tell a lie you would just be
kind of you'd be free basically but at
that layer what would be the most acute
way of not
resisting the um the prospect of telling
the truth what would be the most acute way
truth what would be the most acute way
of not resisting the prospect of telling
the
truth well exactly like recognizing the
the unpleasantness of the idea of it in
the in the idea of and not and and
basically kind and being patient in
regard to it yeah well yeah that would
be a that would be a more subtle
recognition like at that point the most
acute way to not resist be to Simply to
not do it yeah that well that's kind of
what I meant I mean and that you can
carry that principle of all the through
but at that point like if somebody
really is feeling that compulsion you're
not going to recognize exactly because
all feelings and and like you know the
the hindrances and all that stuff would
become apparent once you have not been
uh uh constricted yes on that level yeah
so that's what I meant like it's it's
all but it is still following the same
principle it's just like not
perpetuating that level of it is making
the the subtler level
clear you know from from from that from
that point of view if you're in the
habit of lying habitually you're not
going to see the pressure to lie just
you're not going to see the mental kind
of well you start that's the point
you'll start feeling the pressure but
once you decide to not do it right yeah
yeah so it kind it shows you that that's
kind of why speech needs to be um before
like you need to purify your speech
before you can purify mind just because
I mean that's kind of the the layering
there yeah and and you the the important
point is you have to find and and it
could take some investigation like what
um stage or what layer are you actually
in so what is the thing that you slip on
or in regard to and then you see that
you that's the the stuff you need to
worry about
like at a at the level of a person who
isn't able to keep the BS if they start
worrying about res not resisting the
feeling and and then that's going to be
actually distracting them from what they
actually can do right now and and
factually like cut off an entire like
without remainder that layer is cut off
that layer of Def filment is cut off um
so the noticing what is the actual
compulsion here uh you might be you know
the the the opposite principle is impes
as well if you let's say underestimate
the subtlety of the compulsion and you
think it's just about dealing with the
actions whereas really the stuff that's
propelling you there is your mental
craving now to overly resolve the
situation whereas you're at you're
already restrained but you're kind of
like flaing a dead horse um because you
want now like I I don't want to feel the
pressure to do these actions anymore
even and that's where you would be over
stepping the mark and not seeing that
actually now you you should be working
on a more subtle level of not now on
this mental level revolving around that
restlessness so so yeah it's where where
wherever there is pressure essentially
to to
act so it's um the that internal you
could say that internal uh passion that
that the talks about you could measure
that by saying
not like what do I feel or or what is
there but do I want to act is there a
plan do I have
intentions to act out of this in the
future if that's not
there that's not an internal passion
that you have at that
moment so it's just a basically a
feeling if if truly there is no plan to
give into it no matter how big the wave
is there's no plan to you know jump into
the ocean or run away then that that
isn't there's no problem there anymore
and but the the the well the problem
would be sustaining that because it's so
easy to just fall into one of the other
extremes because again that's the that's
the natural tendency so then um the
other thing I wanted to to mention so
that's already sort of uh brought up for
a second but the P or dependent
origination is usually thought of as
this uh sequence of cause and effect and
that's actually quite obscuring that
view is is is
obscuring this responsibility that we're
talking about the sense of not just
responsibility in a bad sense but in a
good sense as well because if you don't
recognize actually it's on you well that
that does make the practice a lot more
frustrating than it should be
um so the um it's not a cause and effect
in the sense that uh I did something in
the past and now this craving is is like
has to be here because I did something
in the past that's a wrong view um the
craving is there if there is ignorance
now and you have you have a say in that
like you can um first of all recognize
yourself acting out and then restrain
those activities that you're doing on purpose
activities that you're doing on purpose
well not on purpose let's say um it it
does involve intention it never happens
by accident
so
um really should be understood it is the
the the the um epitome of that Timeless uh
the the um epitome of that Timeless uh
nature in the sense that craving is
there not because craving has to be
there craving is there because of
ignorance which means it's like I mean
practically speaking you could say it's
there when it's not known yeah exactly
and that's it you could say craving is
there when craving is not known or
craving is there when feeling is not
known or craving is there when form is
not known any of these aspects you could
take so basically sorry yeah basically like
so basically sorry yeah basically like
you if you think
okay I'm supposed to resolve somehow
that will prevent you from
seeing it's not supposed to resolve it
you're supposed to see with this this is
and then you basically suspend your
preconceived notions of like how much of
it should be there and how much of it
shouldn't be there no what matters is I
sustain the perspective that with this
this is like with this body that's here
subject to aging sickness death while
that is there these thoughts are
happening then and and if you if you maintain that
then and and if you if you maintain that
that um sort of two sides of the coin
and you don't um fall away from it you
you absolutely don't need to worry about
like you know how much thinking is too
much thinking or or you know how long
will this last it doesn't matter anymore
what matters is to sustain that
perspective and this would be going
against the stream yeah that's what that
is the only real really thing that you
can do to prevent yourself from acting
out in the future is like right now the
stuff that's pressuring you to act don't
do it not like you know rearrange the
circumstances so that in the future you
know when it comes up you have like the
perfect plan to deal with it that that's
not how it works it's right now when you
have the inclination to act out of
something seemingly unrelated like you
know the problem is that you tend to
give into lying as we said and then now
you have to you know I don't know go and
watch TV when when um it's clearly
rooted in distraction and it's seemingly
unrelated you would think well you know
if I just come up with the perfect sort
of
psychotherapeutic step-by-step plan to
Never Lie that's how I won't but no you
stop doing these things by by ceasing to
act out of pressure in general um
because it's that's another thing
craving is the the Su is like usually we
tend to assume that craving is some
specific out say I'm craving for this
but actually the the way craving is
defined the sutas is um is like the
craving that leads to repeated repeated
being the lighting here and there or or
now here and now there meaning it's
never about the specific thing it's just
the very general tendency
to lean in those in either towards or
against so it's it it it literally
doesn't matter whether it's towards
lying whether it's towards sensuality
whether it's towards acting out of
aversion all of that is exactly the same
craving and that's why you will see like
if you if you're acting out of
sensuality uh for a while you've been
proliferating that and then something
comes up that before wouldn't have
irritated you as much now it's going to
irritate you because it's the same
craving that's growing even though the
the content of the defat so to speak is
is
different so it's
um fundamentally it's it has to be it
has to start with
um body and speech like restraining
these things practically you will be
much closer to really seeing ptis by
restraining yourself in that
way again with by seeing that
um well the choice recognizing this is a
choice that can simply not make that's
closer much closer to
sing than just you know writing these
charts that people like to fiddle around
with and and all
that I wanted to say I think I think
it's that that point is quite important
though because it can easily I just want
to emphasize it because it might be easy
to to overlook and it is something that
can kind of get in the way the fact that
it's really like the way to do it
correctly is to simp ly not do it
without making that into something else
that you're now like doing or kind of
thinking that in order to not do things
like because that's quite a common thing
as well or something that I used to
think like in order to not do these
things I must I don't know practice a
specific type of mindfulness or be very
aware of like every bodily action or
have a sort of a practice that will
allow me to not do these things no it's
literally just on the level when there's
pressure I don't act out of it to the
extent I'm able to see the pressure and
to the extent I'm able to kind of reveal
my responsibility in it so like if I can
see okay there is a pressure to even
just on the level of breaking the
precepts but I've decided I'm not going
to break the precepts and I'm pressured
to break them but I'm not going to do it
so to that extent I can see I have a
choice and and that's it like I leave it
there and I'm not kind of building
anything else on top of it or doing
anything or seeing it as
or seeing it as
another as another kind of turning that
into aity a new a new activity yeah yeah
and that's that's where it can often
because that that that is exactly the
pressure it's to make this into a new
thing to rely on and why why would you
why would you do that out of pressure
out of craving yeah because basically
like the thing is you're still not
taking responsibility when that happens
is like you basically implicitly you
obviously you're not telling that to
yourself but the idea is no I have the
intention to act because this thing is
here and therefore I need to get rid of
it so that I won't act out but no it's
you choose to act out doesn't matter how
how like even if it's like right flying
in front of your eyes it's you who
chooses to give into it every single
time so then um and that's the same and
and that would be then the same reason
that you would be failing to that would
that would prevent you no matter how far
you take this it's that same reason that
would prevent you from seeing your own
craving because that is exactly the
principle of that's why you don't see
Cravings because I want this because of
this or like because of the attention
being focused it's the things problem
yeah it's the things problem on whatever
subtle or coarse layer yeah it's that
that's actually one of the reasons why
even though you know many people can
keep their precepts and and um be quite
uh wholesome in their outward Behavior
but because they never took the
responsibility for that virtue in the
sense that no it's the problem is not
the the it doesn't have anything to do
with these things arising the problem is
me acting out of them then like you know
you you're keeping the virtue but with
this background view of like you said oh
I need to find all these practices now
that are going to deal with this so that
I don't have to actually restrain myself
that's what you're saying basically um
so uh even though you you might have
practiced virtue for 50 years
in that way it didn't actually develop
well certainly it did develop your mind
to some extent but uh basically like you
basically stopped there you you wouldn't
you couldn't you wouldn't have been able
to go into any deeper layers of actual
mind development which is nothing other
than as I said U before the same way you
just don't uh tell a lie you just don't
engage in sexual intercourse well now
you just don't give in um sensuality ill
will uh uh indolence and lethargy
uh uh indolence and lethargy
restlessness and anxiety and doubt you
don't you just don't give into the five
hindrances and just not giving into the
five hindrances is the pleasure of the
first J you don't need to wait like okay
so I do this practice and then this sort
of uh magical State arises where I not
seclude now I'm secluded from the
hindrances it's you develop it by
understanding what it is and
understanding that extent to which the
thing is there but at the same time
while it's there I'm ref refusing to
give into it either just through a pure
determination or indirectly by
recognizing a context that is there at
the same time with the presence of this
thing and that's the force that you put
on is supposed to achieve and that would
be the
correct this thing is there I'm refusing
to give into this that's that patience
which like it developed to it's it's not
about waiting patient L waiting for you
know for the thing to stop pressuring
you it's like this thing is there I'm
refusing to give into it develop that to
a sufficient extent so that just the
fact that this thing is there in and of
itself will be enough to be free from
the pressure in regard to this like just
knowing just knowing that knowing the
fact that this is there without you know
having basically developed the patient
to an infinite extense would be the
would be I suppose like one of the ways
that you could then describe well you
know whatever it's it's subject to
manifestation all it can do is Manifest
and cease and that's and that's enough
to be free from any pressure in regard
to it it's it's U because that's the
thing um if you expect then that the
understanding will
come uh on that level of some magical
Revelations and
and uh visions and stuff that comes up
when you finally got rid of the pressure
that's not actually teaching you how to
deal or how to um you know survive let's
say in the midst of what your senses
actually are in times when they go back
to their usual state which is inevitable
even the sutas say like if an narad gets
too um distracted with Fame honor
possessions and that sort of thing they
will lose their Sade so their senses
will go back to their natural state but
that that uh unshakable liberation of
Mind as it's described in the sutas
which is like that recognition that no
matter how loud this gets how pressuring
this gets I always have the choice even
if it's just a tiny millimeter or
nanometer space to remain completely
uninvolved with
it and that's starts with like you you
try to figure that out abstractly it's
not going to work it's you you start to
see it by your for yourself factually uh
just by keeping the precepts like the
the the suas would say um somebody who
devolves precepts they would um they
would have this uh what's it called
unblemished Joy internally so it's not a
joy of um of some other sort of Mass
Massage that that came over you out of
nowhere it's the joy of seeing no wait
this stuff that I previously felt was
being imposed on me actually wasn't it
was entirely my like I was basically
torturing Myself by giving into this
stuff and now you see that and now you
see it can't come in by itself like you
are the one who who ushers it in so um
that gives rise to the the the type of
peace that and the type of peace that
actually develop vs you so that in the
future you won't be falling for that
trap again not like temporarily you went
into a different dimension now you come
back and the same problem is there which
is what usually
happens um so the the um the thing it
shouldn't be viewed as a as a sequence
neither in multiple lives nor in in span
of 5 Seconds it's uh everything all of
that is just happening at the same time
and you can't sort of um put yourself
outside of of that structure like um
observe it from the outside let's say
you are always the one who is like you
are you you exist to the extent that
that structure is
there that's basically it so anything
you do you think you're watching you're
your Consciousness coming passing like
this all of that is already within
ignorance already Within SAR is already
within namarupa so it's just like
proliferating further while the actual
stuff is happening there behind you so
say um so by by cultivating this on on
whichever level the person is at the
moment like that they've been able to
remain stable in then uh that's the
that's the um it's the same training all
along it's just uh the same principle
developed on more and more subtle layers
and the um that's why in the sutas you
you would sometimes find not
necessarily like concrete meditation
object so to say it would just say oh
develop the perception of
Abandonment develop uh non Delight in
the whole world develop um you know in
some C it would say like just develop
the effort that you will not give into
un wholesome States
because it's never about some object
that will later in
time give you a a vacation from this
it's about these the objects quote
unquote the suas are that the suas give
are all for that same purpose of
maintaining perspective to the extent that you won't
perspective to the extent that you won't
act out while that thing is there but
all of these atianas and stuff that
that's exclusively for the mental level
really like to once you your body and
speech are fully restrained and now your
mind is the one that's kind of uh like
going too far in either direction let's
say now that's when the saatana has come
in like that's going to help you keep
perspective in the face of your own
thinking not to get rid of it but to but
to see for what it is and that's the
first J uh thinking and pondering is
still there but that unshakable
perspective that prevents you from um
falling into it let's say while it's
happening um so yeah then you know it
goes further into
um second Janna third Janna but it's
always the same
principle so
um and it that's why it wouldn't either
be a matter of you sort of committing to
the practice of the batana
for a certain amount of time period of
time so that then this result comes of
the of the piece whatever if you if you
have that view you still haven't
understood what that right endurance is
it's like no right now all that matters
is that right now I am not acting out of
sensual desire of aversion of indolence
of anxiety and of Doubt when will the
Jan come well see that's right there is
you acting out of restlessness again if
you don't keep not to get rid of it but
if you don't keep perspective in regard
to that thought and you don't include it
within the same other stuff and you
start to give it some gratuitous
priority that's why you you won't be
getting J so you see um at no point
would it ever be useful to ask or think
in terms of
when or what actually even that's the
other thing like there is no because
that will always kind of come with
something like whether some thought some
idea some
notion that's
this is the priority or this is like the
thing that is kind of justifiable to
focus on it to think about it to worry
about it to have some kind of pressure
in regard to us like whe you know
whatever because it's about the first J
when will it come because it's not and
that one is wholesome that one's okay
exactly or like I factually did
something bad in the past now therefore
it's you know it's kind of Justified to
worry about it it's not because it's
rooted in the pressure it doesn't matter
matter what it is and that's why it's
like you know even in these you know
these um early verses and so on where he
you know that somebody's saying I see
the the pure the highest freedom from
disease and so on like and then he's
kind of criticizing him for resting on
that uh thing that he has seen he's not
denying that well no because you just
saw some kind of low thing and there's
actually something much higher it's like
doesn't matter how high or how pure the
thing he saw was the attitude of resting
on it like taking it for
granted um leaning on it finding safety
in it that's what the problem always is
so that's kind of another and that's
another thing where you would be kind of
um they would have to go together
basically like if it's about this thing
arising it doesn't matter whether it's
seen heard thought cognized it has to
arise in time
so that would be like the the other I
suppose way you could use that as a as a
measure like your mind is resting on
some something even the the the hope that you
something even the the the hope that you
know if I just stick to this practice
long enough the J will come or
Enlightenment will come yeah
Enlightenment will come and what is that
well that's cognized exactly cogniz
cogniz that's an idea yeah and then you
sort of don't you you question
everything else like everything else you
you you don't
you don't welcome you don't Delight in
but that no that that one's
fine so um that's that's the only reason
why and then
um the the it doesn't mean of course
that you don't make efforts like because
we're saying okay don't worry about
what's going to happen later no it's you
realize you have to make the effort but
the effort is always now and
expectations have to be included within
that effort so you have like a I don't
know um a compulsion to to to wonder about
um a compulsion to to to wonder about
when when will I get the right view or
when will I finally be able to clear
myself from the FAS
but see you you um you deal with it you
get closer not by following that line of
thought but by right now not
gratuitously forgiving or giving space
for that to continue and you're you're
doing the work now like so by abandoning
expectations for enlightenment having already
for enlightenment having already
purified the coarser stuff of course
that's how you're actually getting
closer it doesn't again you shouldn't be
confused with these common views like oh
there's nothing to be attained or or um
you know soent is just another becoming
no like you you should be aiming for it
but you should understand how it is yeah
exactly
yeah that's also why like this
um know it's um something that's said
often like that what needs to be
understood is you can't own things even
if you want to I think just by virtue of
like hearing that quite often you can
forget the significance or like of it
and really the point is like why why do
you say you can't own things even if you
want to the point is that you know when
when you're hearing that it's you want
to kind of I want to see how this is not
mine that's like the attitude of
somebody you know who wants to practice
I want to not own it and it's you
wanting to not own it that's kind of
preventing you from seeing that you that
you can't own
it
um
yeah so like including that's the point
like including that even in um just be
just being properly aware of it then
that's the other thing I was going to
say like because you can sort of then after
like because you can sort of then after
the effect okay yeah I shouldn't do that
and I shouldn't act out of it but
ultimately we'll have to kind of come
down to recognizing that that desire or
that craving while it's there and that in and
craving while it's there and that in and
of itself would literally cancel it out
that's why like
n um
like it said in the beginning you know
somebody sees um he feels he whates it say he
sees um he feels he whates it say he
feels the sight and there is passion for
his sights internally so he sees there
is passion for sights internally in me
and then um in the second part it said
he feels the sight and there is no
passion for the sights internally and
there's a lot of the sutas carry the
same principle so it kind of sounds like
these kind of it's sort of talking about
two different people on two different
occasions okay one feels the sight
passion and he knows that there's
passion for sights internally and then
later on a different occasion somebody
else uh feels the sight but no passion
whereas actually it's almost like I
would say it's describing the
same the same thing from or the from two
different perspectives in other words
like the person who recogn upon
recognizing there is passion for sights
internally immediately immediately which
switches it to there is no passion for
sides internally because that passion
cannot exist in the environment of
knowledge where there's no ignorance so
it's like knowing it is the is the
abandonment that is that that's a the I
mean I have mentioned it a few times
already but the thing is it's probably
easily overlooked
like and that's one of those things that
clicks only later you heard it a million
times no the craving is not there by
itself craving is only there when there
is ignorance and every every Buddhist
would say oh yeah of course but no like
factually when you're trying to get rid
of stuff it's the usual way of
practicing you carry the implication
that the craving is sad of like
primordial and it's there on its own
yeah but actually no like the craving is
the craving is there to the extent that
ignorance is there but if you if you
overlook if you don't put things in the
right order
basically uh you you won't be actually
dealing with so really you're going to
be dealing with the symptoms of craving
no doesn't matter how much you think
you're dealing with the actual craving
so um the that's the but that's a
difficult thing like it's it's um it
doesn't doesn't give that
immediate satisfaction satisfaction that
you expect
expect
thinking maybe one way to understand
that practically or at least to kind of
get an idea of it is that like if you
think of craving
as as a thing something else that I have
to deal with it's not that's that's not
going to be it that's going to be a
symptom of this it's basically the
closest thing you can find to your point
of view it's right where you are like
what what's what's the closest thing to
you would be where you would find your
person and that can only be revealed not
by trying to figure it out but by if you
have removed these more subtle layers
like there's always going to be a layer
that you can see as as I've repeated
multiple times so that's the layer where
you work on removing that layer is
what's going to make the next layer
apparent then removing that layer is
going to make but if you're here and
then you're trying to figure out like
okay so how what is it that you know is
preventing AR anagami from becoming Arun
and then you're like down here that's
not going to work so um and then the the
related to what you said about craving
um that's the yeah that's exactly what I
just mentioned that it's it Delights
here in there it it it has nothing to do
with what it is it's the principle of
like taking things up wherever it can so
if you if you if for as long as you
think that the craving is this
object by definition you you're not
seeing craving or this feeling or
whatever it it simply cannot be
something specific
um so all of that is like you know would
be recognized by first as we talked
about before seeing the signs of your
mind and and learning what Y is and so
on but um yeah so actually the the Su um
it's good that you brought that up
because it does sound and I the first
time I read it I do remember I thought
like okay yeah this is talking about two
different people or something but no
like the suta itself is saying the dhama
is timeless exactly and is is using that
to explain how the dama is timeless so
it's basically
saying without any time involved a
person can go from their being passion
internally to their being no passion
internally and it's not because um it's
not that they couldn't do it because
they haven't been practicing long enough
that's not the primary cause they
couldn't do it because they didn't know
how to do it so that's why like you know
from the very beginning everyone can be
free from greed of version and delusion
it's not there's nothing blocking um
that like like a magical sort of energy
that you clear out through the practice
it is always the only what thing that's
blocking it is great inversion and
delusions yeah yeah and it feeds itself
obviously so G version delusion feeds
ignorance ignorance feeds G version
delusion so um so basically like you
could be in our today if you just
understand fully how not to have passion
internally that there's nothing like
like um that there is no reason why you have
um that there is no reason why you have
to uh why time has to pass practically
it will so don't be expecting like I
can't get Enlighten overnight
but if you understand it that way you
will actually see it is always fully
your responsibility nothing can come and
responsibility nothing can come and
that's why nothing can come in between
it because see that's the thing if if
craving if freedom from craving freedom
from ignorance all these things actually
required time or or had anything to do
with time once you achieved it there will be
time once you achieved it there will be
no guarantee that it won't come back
like uh the once you achieve the freedom
from it there will be no guarantee that
it won't come back because it meant that
it was basically like external to you
imposed on you and then if you were free
from it that would be basically
circumstantial even if it lasts was
something that happened to you yeah yeah
exactly so something that happened to
you something that um that just came to
sort of replace the stuff that was there
before but no because it is fully based
on
understanding like can you
forget something when you were assuming
something when you were assuming
something and then you know the actual
nature of it how can you ever forget you
can forget specific things you can
forget um you know uh where certain
place lies in the map or something but
that fundament mental knowledge is
something that well it pertains to the
nature of your very experience so for as
long as experience is there you won't be
able to forget it because every single
phenomenon involves that same nature so
you you basically it's impossible for
you to forget for as long as you're
alive so
um that's in a position to something
that uh just happens even if it
supposedly through your effort and and
your years of practice the fact that you
still thought of it is okay yeah time
after this 20
years like if you still have the view no
all of this effort was necessary to
bring me to this point because it was
like loading up this this um this meter
or something that means you don't see
anotherone the right level you think
it's you're basically just uh dealing
with circumstances
it should be
like when you're free from it you see if
if back if from day one I would have
known this I would have been free from
day one that time was strictly speaking
it was like
necessary because ignorance is
beginningless but it's not intrinsic to
the process of purification that's why
like bah and stuff you know he he went
from pu to Arun in basically a moment
I was maybe you could even get a glimpse
of that on the level of
um back down to like even just the level
of keeping the precepts again
because you know keeping the precepts in
a way I think it can often sound like
okay yeah this is something you now have
to do and take on but even somebody who
is completely unrestrained like do they
spend do you spend more time breaking
the precepts or not breaking the
precepts well actually I spend much more time not
well actually I spend much more time not
breaking the precepts so all I have to
do is on very certain very specific
occasions not make choices that I would
have you know made in the past and I
realized I find myself
already in a in a Stace that was kind of
already there under my feet in a way
like I I and I was just um not in it
because of kind of going out of your way
in in a way and I suppose like for some
from the point of view of somebody who
is habitually breaking the precepts and
not keeping the virtue that is what kind
of feels like the Natural State feels e
feels automatic feels effortless but you
realize actually well which which kind
of is more complicated basically it more
complicated to like you know go out of
my way tell a you know misrepresent the
truth tell a lie is it more complicated
have to you
know uh uh whatever um steal something
from somebody else uh kill
whatever it's more
complicated in a to put it to put it in
that way or it's it involves more effort
than not doing these things and and you
were already spending more time have
having um having more of your life in
the state of not breaking the precepts
so it's more like just to kind of well
you would realize as suppose once you
developed this that you actually were
just um developing something that was
already kind of there in an inent form
and that was that you could have
accessed that you could have always
accessed it was not something that you
had to go out and like seek and
gain so it's not like a like let's say
you know um a pilot like
factually it is impossible that someone
has never driven a plane with for and he
just gets in somebody tells him
something and he does it
perfectly because that's a mundane skill
and that's why treating the dhama as a
skill is extremely misguided it's like
no it's from day one if you were if your
own as a Buddha said Dust In Your Eyes
was not there this would have been
obvious there was like the the time
really you could say that's the best way
to put it the time seeing it didn't
require re time where required time was
taking up the Dust In Your Eyes that
prevented you from seeing what was
already there the whole time